Princeton University Library Collection of Patrick Henry Materials, 1743-1796: Finding Aid C1165
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University Library Collection of Patrick Henry Materials
1743-1796
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799
C1165
1 box
0.2 linear feet
Consists of selected manuscript material by and about American attorney, politician, and planter Patrick Henry (1736-1799).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of selected manuscript material by and about Patrick Henry (1736-1799), including signed autograph letters to family and associates; documents and notes regarding legal, property, and financial matters; and engraved portraits of Henry.
Arrangement
Items are arranged by accession.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Custodial History
The collection was formed as a result of a Departmental practice of combining into one collection material of various accessions relating to a particular person, family, or subject.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Promissory Note in the Hand of Patrick Henry, Signed by Jacob Puckett was a gift of Pierre F. Cook (1892) in 1931. (AM 9875).
Letter to Thomas Madison and receipt dated June 8, 1765, were a gift of Cyrus H. McCormick in April 1947. (AM 13366)
Letter to Robert Carter and receipts for October 1764 and May 1765 were a gift of David S. Elkind (1973), in October 2006. (AM 2007-37)
Purchases from 2007 to the present have been made with support from The Barksdale-Dabney-Henry Fund for Research and Teaching on Patrick Henry and Early Americana (AM 2007-66, AM 2008-66, AM 2009-34, AM 2009-40, AM 2009-115, AM 2010-26, AM 2014-59, AM 2016-23, AM 2017-62, AM 2018-44, AM 2019-129, AM 2020-72).
Appraisal
No material was separated during 2013-2020 processing.
Revolutionaries -- United States -- 18th century .; Slaveholders -- Virginia -- 18th century .; Slavery -- Virginia -- 18th century -- Sources.; Virginia -- History -- 1775-1865 -- Sources.; Correspondence -- 18th century.; Documents -- 18th century.; Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799
- Promissory Note, 1793 February 22; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  The collection is open for research use.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  AM 9875
  Scope and Contents
  In the hand of Patrick Henry, signed by Jacob Puckett
- Letter to His Brother-in-Law, Thomas Madison (1746–1798), 1789 September 28; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
  AM 13366
  Regards a bond of Henry's brother.
- Receipt and Letter to Robert Carter, 1765; 1789; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  AM 2007-37
  Letter, dated July 24, 1789, regards a legal matter.
- Letter to His Daughter, Elizabeth (Betsey) Aylett, and Steel Engraving of Henry, 1794 May 3; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  AM 2007-66
- Letter Concerning Will of Israel Christian, 1788 June 19; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  AM 2008-43
- Receipt for Shoes and Saddle Cloth for Henry's Nephew, John H. Christian, 1795, 1889; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  AM 2008-86
  Signed by cobbler Ephraim Potts
  Includes an accompanying explanatory letter (1889)
- Letter to Spencer Roane (Son-in-Law), 1786 November 14; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
  AM 2009-34
- One-Page "Opinion" Regarding a Land Survey, circa 1831; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
  AM 2009-40
- Letter to "Sir" (Henry Lee?), 1795 February 14; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
  AM 2009-115
  Declining to take a law case involving an influential Fairfax family.
- Letter to Philip Payne Concerning Supplies for Persons Enslaved by Henry, 1794 July 30; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
  AM 2010-26
- Letter to Colonel Joseph Martin Regarding Policy toward American Indians, 1784 December 13; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
  AM 2013-118
- Letter to Unidentified Correspondent Regarding the Sale of His Plantation, Red Hill, 1796 March 14; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter to Benjamin Harrison, approximately 1726-1791, 1779 May 25; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
  AM 2014-59
  Addressed to the Virginia delegate, the letter is about two persons jailed for suspected "wicked intentions."
- Outgoing Letter Concerning the Selling of Enslaved Persons to Purchase Yazoo Land, and Engraving of Henry, 1790 January 12; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
  AM 2016-23
  Sent from Prince Edward County, Virginia, Henry writes about selling enslaved persons to raise money to purchase Yazoo land (portions of present day Alabama and Mississippi).
  The engraving, made from an Alonzo Chappel painting of Henry seated with a pen and notebook, is undated.
- Documents Regarding Henry's Purchase of Lands on Leatherwood Creek, Henry County, 1743-1783; 1778; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
  AM 2017-62
  Consists of three documents related to the purchase of lands for Patrick Henry's Leatherwood Plantation. In one document, dated November 27, 1778, Martin Key agrees to allow Patrick Henry to settle on land on Leatherwood Creek in Henry County, Virginia, which Henry purchased from Thomas Lomax, but was involved in a legal dispute. Another is a May 29, 1778, document signed by Thomas Lomax transferring 9,990 acres of land on Leatherwood Creek to Patrick Henry. The third is a complaint for the Court of Chancery case of Lomax v. Randolph concerning a tract of land, circa 1743 (filed April 3, 1783).
- Letter to Henry Lee (1756-1818), 1795 April 7; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
  AM 2018-44
  Consists of a one-page signed autograph letter from Patrick Henry in Red Hill, Virginia, to Major-General Henry "Light-Horse Harry" Lee III. Henry opens the letter reporting that he has again been asked by "the Executive" (President George Washington) to administer the Fairfax estate, likely referring to George William Fairfax, whose estate neighbored Mount Vernon. Fairfax had left Virginia in 1773, giving Washington power of attorney, but had died in England in 1787. Henry continues seeking Lee's assistance in selling "about 10 tracts of land in No. Carolina from 15 to 20 miles from Fayetteville. They contain about 9000 acres, are choice rice lands..." Henry also describes land at Cape Henry and elsewhere.
- Engraved Portrait of Patrick Henry, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Consists of an engraved portrait of Patrick Henry, engraved by E. Wellmore from a painting by J.B. Longacre after an original miniature in possession of John S. Fleming of Virginia. The engraving is signed by Patrick Henry.
- Patrick Henry Letter to the County Lieutenant of Berkeley, 1777 November 12; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
  AM 2019-129
  One letter, written in Williamsburg, from Patrick Henry as Governor of Virginia, in which he arranges for salt provisions for the Virginia militia "that have joined Genl Washington."
- Patrick Henry Document Certifying Land Allotment to Thomas Chandler, 1785 February 28; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
  AM 2020-72
  Consists of a printed document completed by hand and signed by Patrick Henry, certifying that the representative of Thomas Chandler is entitled to the proportion of land allowed a Lieutenant of the State Navy for three years service.
- Patrick Henry Letter Fragment to Moses Smith, 1794 February 14; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)